Inventory of the Howard A. Meyerhoff Papers, 1898-1988
University of Wyoming. American Heritage Center.
Howard A. Meyerhoff papers
1898-1988
Meyerhoff, Howard A. (Howard Augustus), 1899-
03681
11.20 cubic feet (13 boxes)
University of Wyoming. American Heritage Center.
The Howard A. Meyerhoff Collection contains the personal and professional papers of Howard A. Meyerhoff, a geologist, professor of geology at Smith College, and chair of the editorial board for the American Association for the Advancement of Science.
Biography of Howard A. Meyerhoff
Howard A. Meyerhoff (1899-1982), a geologist, was professor of geology at Smith College from 1925-1949, administrative secretary and chair of the editorial board for the American Association for the Advancement of Science from 1949-1953, a member of the Scientific Manpower Commission from 1953-1965, and head of the Geology Department at the University of Pennsylvania from 1962-1967. He was also chairman of the board of Propper-McCallum Hosiery Co. from 1938-1947, a mediator for the National War Labor Board from 1943-1944, a founder of GeoSurveys, Inc., an expert on copyright, a founder of the Northeastern Section of the Geological Society of America, an investor in mining ventures and a consultant. Meyerhoff was an authority on the geology of Puerto Rico and the Caribbean Basin and a critic of the plate tectonic and continental drift theories. He was author of numerous articles, including some co-authored by his son A.A. Meyerhoff.
Scope and Content
Collection contains business and personal correspondence (1925-1982); professional files; field notebooks (1916-1933); maps; manuscripts; memorandums; reports; speeches; legal documents; biographical information; and miscellaneous other materials. Correspondents include geologists, business associates and General Lewis B. Hershey, who directed military drafts from World War II through the Vietnam War.
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions on the materials for research purposes, and the collection is open to the public.
Related Materials
There are no known other archival collections created by Howard A. Meyerhoff at the date of processing.
Acquisition Information
Received from Howard A. Meyerhoff, 1971-1978 and Sophie Meyerhoff, 1982-1987.
Access Terms
American Association for the Advancement of Science.; Geological Society of America. Northeastern Section.; American Association of Petroleum Geologists.; American Institute of Professional Geologists.; Scientific Manpower Commission.; National Science Foundation (U.S.); Propper-McCallum Hosiery Company.; Geosurveys, Inc.; Mount Pleasant Mines, Inc.; United States. National War Labor Board (1942-1945); Geology -- United States.; Geology -- Puerto Rico.; Geology -- Caribbean Area.; Manpower policy -- United States.; Copyright -- United States.; Mines and mineral resources -- Colorado.; Mines and mineral resources -- United States.; Mines and mineral resources -- Canada.; Labor supply -- United States.; Draft -- United States.; Scientists -- United States.;; Field notes.; Technical reports.; Memorandums.; Legal documents.; Speeches.; Maps.; Geologists.;; Meyerhoff, A. A. (Arthur Augustus), 1928-; Teichert, Curt, 1905-1996.; Condon, Edward Uhler, 1902-1974.; Hershey, Lewis Blaine, 1893-1977.; Campbell, Ian, 1899-1978.; Wynne-Jones, Sydney Thomas.; Woodward, Herbert Preston, 1899-1968.
Education; Colleges and Universities; Science, Technology and Health; Science; Agriculture and Natural Resources; Mines and Mineral Resources
Container List
- Series I. Correspondence
  This series contains personal and professional correspondence, arranged by date and then alphabetically by correspondent.
  - Correspondence, 1930-1931 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1932-1934 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1934-1936 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1937-1952 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1948-1959 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1953 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1953-1959 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1953-1961 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1956-1957 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1958 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1959 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1960-1962 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1960-1969 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1961-1962 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1963 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1963-1964 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1964-1965 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1963-1969 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1965-1966 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1966 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1967 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1967-1968 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1968-1973 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1969-1974 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1970-1973 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1970-1979 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1974 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1975 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1976 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1977 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1977 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1978 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1979 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1980-1981 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, undated (Box 3)
  - Correspondence- A, 1978-1982 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence- Addresses, 1959-1965 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence- Malcolm Ater, 1961-1964 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence- B, 1933-1982 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence- Dr. N.L. Britton, 1924-1934 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence- C, 1958-1981 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence- Dr Ian Campbell, 1955-1972 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence- D, 1968-1974 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence- Dr C.L. Dake, 1923-1934 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence- Stuart T. Danforth, 1933-1934 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence- Roy E. Dickerson, 1933-1935 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence- E, 1938-1963 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence- Dr. Frederick Ehrenfeld, 1938-1939 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence- F, 1949-1982 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence- Julian Feiss, 1967-1981 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence- G, 1963-1977 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence- Dr. Filmore Garner, 1978-1981 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence- Gene Gressley, 1978-1981 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence- H, 1928-1981 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence- Ethel Harris, 1978-1979 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence- Dr. Marshall Howe, 1935-1936 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence- J, 1964-1967 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence- Dr. D.W. Johnson, 1926-1940 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence- Senator Lyndon B. Johnson (copies), 1956-1958 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence- Senator Lyndon B. Johnson (originals), 1956-1958 (Box 12)
  - Correspondence- K, 1926-1972 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence- Frank Kottlowski, 1979-1981 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence- L, 1952-1981 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence- Dr. Frederic B. Loomis, 1926-1936 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence- M, 1959-1982 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence- William MacDonald, 1966-1969 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence- Meyerhoff Family, 1903-1982 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence- Muccia & Muccia, 1962-1963 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence- N, 1978-1987 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence- Newspapers and Magazines, 1956-1981 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence- O, 1978-1981 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence- P, 1927-1981 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence- Edmund F. Pawlowicz, 1978-1987 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence- R, 1928-1981 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence- S, 1934-1981 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence- Frank Skidmore, 1955-1970 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence- Grayson Swailes, 1978-1980 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence- T, 1925-1938 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence- Nouri Tawfiq, 1960-1970 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence- Curt Teichert, 1975-1979 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence- Tulsa University Geology, 1970-1971 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence- U-V, 1967-1981 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence- Unidentified, 1968-1981 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence- Dr. Joseph Valiunas, 1963-1966 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence- W, 1935-1982 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence- Richard Walls, 1973-1978 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence- S.T. Wynne-Jones, 1964-1975 (Box 4)
- Series II. Personal Papers
  This series contains personal and family files, arranged by alphabetically.
  - Biographical Sketches, 1955-1959 (Box 4)
  - Clubs and Associations- Cosmo Club, 1974-1977 (Box 4)
  - Clubs and Associations- Kiwanis Club, 1973-1977 (Box 4)
  - Clubs and Associations- John Frank Stevens Hall of Fame, 1972-1976 (Box 4)
  - Correspondents, 1988 (Box 4)
  - CVs and Resumes, 1961 (Box 4)
  - Family- Arthur Meyerhoff, 1968-1978 (Box 4)
  - Family- Sophie Meyerhoff, 1898-1971 (Box 4)
  - Family- Other, 1972-1978 (Box 4)
  - IDs, 1971-1972 (Box 4)
  - Itineraries, 1974-1975 (Box 4)
  - Marriage, 1921 (Box 4)
  - Memberships and Honors, 1921-1981 (Box 4)
  - Memorials, 1982-1983 (Box 4)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1963-1978 (Box 4)
  - Photographs, 1943 (Box 4)
  - Poetry, 1971 (Box 4)
  - Political Ephemera, 1968-1978 (Box 4)
  - Property, 1960 (Box 4)
  - Wills, 1946 (Box 4)
- Series III. Professional Papers
  This series contains professional papers, arranged alphabetically by company or association.
  - American Association for the Advancement of Science- Board of Directors, 1953-1954 (Box 4)
  - American Association for the Advancement of Science- Committees, 1952-1953 (Box 4)
  - American Association for the Advancement of Science- Correspondence, Condon et al, 1953 (Box 4)
  - American Association for the Advancement of Science- Council, 1953-1954 (Box 4)
  - American Association for the Advancement of Science- Press Releases and News Clippings, 1952-1954 (Box 4)
  - American Association for the Advancement of Science- Science, 1931-1962 (Box 4)
  - American Association for the Advancement of Science- Statements on Stepping Down, 1953 (Box 4)
  - American Association of Petroleum Geologists, 1963-1981 (Box 4)
  - American Institute of Professional Geologists, 1962-1976 (Box 5)
  - American Security Council, 1975 (Box 5)
  - Bureau of Employment Security, 1963-1965 (Box 5)
  - Columbia University, 1928 (Box 5)
  - Committee to Investigate Copyright Problems- Administrative Files, 1950-1967 (Box 5)
  - Committee to Investigate Copyright Problems- Clearinghouse Study, 1963-1965 (Box 5)
  - Committee to Investigate Copyright Problems- Control and Accountability Study, 1972 (Box 5)
  - Committee to Investigate Copyright Problems- Correspondence, 1967-1971 (Box 5)
  - Committee to Investigate Copyright Problems- Drafts and Notes, 1959-1970 (Box 5)
  - Committee to Investigate Copyright Problems- Hearings, 1960-1967 (Box 5)
  - Committee to Investigate Copyright Problems- Legal and Economic Report, 1967 (Box 5)
  - Committee to Investigate Copyright Problems- Legislation, 1964-1969 (Box 5)
  - Committee to Investigate Copyright Problems- Meeting Proceedings, 1960-1968 (Box 5)
  - Committee to Investigate Copyright Problems- Meetings and Schedules, 1959-1971 (Box 5)
  - Committee to Investigate Copyright Problems- Memos, 1959-1968 (Box 5)
  - Committee to Investigate Copyright Problems- Photocopying, 1970 (Box 5)
  - Committee to Investigate Copyright Problems- Proposals, 1960-1970 (Box 5)
  - Committee to Investigate Copyright Problems- Publications, 1967 (Box 5)
  - Committee to Investigate Copyright Problems- Research- Bibliographies, 1963-1964 (Box 5)
  - Committee to Investigate Copyright Problems- Research- Conferences and Meetings, 1964-1972 (Box 5)
  - Committee to Investigate Copyright Problems- Research- Legal, 1965-1972 (Box 5)
  - Committee to Investigate Copyright Problems- Research- Libray and Publishing Correspondence, 1959-1971 (Box 5)
  - Committee to Investigate Copyright Problems- Research- News Clippings, 1961-1970 (Box 5)
  - Committee to Investigate Copyright Problems- Research- Periodicals, 1960-1968 (Box 6)
  - Committee to Investigate Copyright Problems- Research- Speeches, 1965-1971 (Box 6)
  - Committee to Investigate Copyright Problems- Study Group A, 1959 (Box 6)
  - Conferences- Soil Science Conference, 1950 (Box 6)
  - Conferences- Soil Science Conference- Papers, 1950 (Box 6)
  - Dominican Republic- Aluminum and Bauxite, 1944-1945 (Box 6)
  - Dominican Republic- Economic Geography, 1937 (Box 6)
  - Dominican Republic- El Seybo, undated (Box 6)
  - Dominican Republic- General Reports, 1926-1939 (Box 6)
  - Dominican Republic- Iron, 1922-1947 (Box 6)
  - Dominican Republic- Mineral Resources Report, 1937 (Box 6)
  - Dominican Republic- Mining Laws, undated (Box 6)
  - Geological Society of America, 1964-1974 (Box 6)
  - Geological Society of America- Northeastern Section, 1964-1967 (Box 6)
  - GeoSurveys- Annual Reports, 1973-1980 (Box 6)
  - GeoSurveys- Board of Directors, 1973-1980 (Box 6)
  - GeoSurveys- Financial Reports, 1974-1980 (Box 6)
  - GeoSurveys- Correspondence, 1959-1981 (Box 6)
  - GeoSurveys- Mines- Canada, Mount Pleasant- Financial Reports, 1963-1965 (Box 6)
  - GeoSurveys- Mines- Canada, Mount Pleasant- Metalurgical Reports, 1963 (Box 7)
  - GeoSurveys- Mines- Canada, Mount Pleasant- Ore Reports, 1963 (Box 7)
  - GeoSurveys- Mines- Canada, Mount Pleasant- Program Summary, 1962-1966 (Box 7)
  - GeoSurveys- Mines- Canada, Mount Pleasant- Prospectus, 1962-1964 (Box 7)
  - GeoSurveys- Mines- Canada, Mount Pleasant- Tin Deposit Reports, undated (Box 7)
  - GeoSurveys- Mines- Canada, Portneuf Mines Corporation, 1966-1967 (Box 7)
  - GeoSurveys- Mines- Mexico, 1965-1966 (Box 7)
  - GeoSurveys- Mines- United States, Arizona, undated (Box 7)
  - GeoSurveys- Mines- United States, California, 1980 (Box 7)
  - GeoSurveys- Mines- United States, Colorado, 1972-1974 (Box 7)
  - GeoSurveys- Mines- United States, Missouri, 1978 (Box 7)
  - GeoSurveys- Mines- United States, Montana, Judith Gold, 1971-1973 (Box 7)
  - GeoSurveys- Mines- United States, Montana, North Moccasin, 1976 (Box 7)
  - GeoSurveys- Mines- United States, New Mexico, 1959-1980 (Box 7)
  - GeoSurveys- Mines- United States, New York, Atlantic Cement Company, 1959-1961 (Box 7)
  - GeoSurveys- Mines- United States, South Carolina, 1980 (Box 7)
  - GeoSurveys- Mines- Venezuela, 1963-1981 (Box 7)
  - GeoSurveys- Newspaper Article, 1961-1967 (Box 7)
  - GeoSurveys- Newspaper Article-"Manpower in a Column" for Geotimes, 1961-1967 (Box 7)
  - GeoSurveys- Newspaper Article-Research, 1967 (Box 8)
  - GeoSurveys- News Coverage, 1972-1980 (Box 8)
  - GeoSurveys- Press Releases, 1955-1957 (Box 8)
  - GeoSurveys- Press Releases- Drafts, 1957 (Box 8)
  - GeoSurveys- Press Releases, 1958-1960 (Box 8)
  - GeoSurveys- Press Releases, 1962-1964 (Box 8)
  - GeoSurveys- Press Releases, 1966-1969 (Box 8)
  - GeoSurveys- Securities and Exchange Commission, 1979-1981 (Box 8)
  - GeoSurveys- Stockholders, 1972-1979 (Box 8)
  - Health Career Handbook Committee, 1963-1965 (Box 8)
  - International Association for the Exchange of Students for Technical Experience, 1967-1968 (Box 9)
  - National Association of Geology Teachers, 1967-1975 (Box 9)
  - National Science Foundation, 1954-1956 (Box 9)
  - Office of Emergency Planning- Conferences, 1960-1965 (Box 9)
  - Office of Emergency Planning- Manpower Reservists, 1965-1966 (Box 9)
  - Office of Emergency Planning- Memos, 1963-1968 (Box 9)
  - Office of Emergency Planning- Newsletters, 1963-1970 (Box 9)
  - Office of Emergency Planning- Pamphlets and Publications, 1962-1967 (Box 9)
  - Office of Emergency Planning- Speeches, 1964-1965 (Box 9)
  - Panama Sea Levels Hearing, 1960-1965 (Box 9)
  - Pennsylvania Civil Service Commission, 1965 (Box 9)
  - Pennsylvania Department of Public Instruction, 1966-1967 (Box 9)
  - Propper-McCallum Hosiery Company, 1937-1938 (Box 9)
  - Research- Aluminum, 1955-1956 (Box 9)
  - Research- Charts, 1962 (Box 9)
  - Research- Field Books, 1916-1933 (Box 9)
  - Research- Geology Education, undated (Box 9)
  - Research- Gila River Case, 1978-1980 (Box 9)
  - Research- Government Reports, 1959-1962 (Box 9)
  - Research- Grazing- Inspections, 1951-1961 (Box 9)
  - Research- Grazing- Letters and Memos, 1906-1956 (Box 9)
  - Research- General Lewis B. Hershey, 1960-1977 (Box 9)
  - Research- General Lewis B. Hershey Funeral (2 audio cassette tapes), 1977 (Box 13)
  - Research- J. Herbert Hollman, 1968 (Box 9)
  - Research- Legal, 1957 (Box 10)
  - Research- McCarthy Trials, 1953-1954 (Box 10)
  - Research- Mines- Australia, 1975 (Box 10)
  - Research- Mines- Canada, 1975 (Box 10)
  - Research- Mines- Canada, Ontario, Burnt Brush River Properties, 1964 (Box 10)
  - Research- Mines- Cuba, Yao Valley, 1944-1966 (Box 10)
  - Research- Mines- Mexico, 1964-1965 (Box 10)
  - Research- Mines- Mexico, Coahuila, undated (Box 10)
  - Research- Mines- United Kingdom, 1963 (Box 10)
  - Research- Mines- United States, Arizona, 1972-1973 (Box 10)
  - Research- Mines- United States, California, 1981 (Box 10)
  - Research- Mines- United States, Colorado, Cripple Creek, 1941-1974 (Box 10)
  - Research- Mines- United States, Colorado, Gold Links, 1958-1974 (Box 10)
  - Research- Mines- United States, Colorado, Sugar Loaf, 1963 (Box 10)
  - Research- Mines- United States, New Mexico, 1958 (Box 10)
  - Research- Mines- United States, Ohio, 1969 (Box 10)
  - Research- Mines- United States, Texas, 1959 (Box 10)
  - Research- Mines- Venezuela, 1961-1963 (Box 10)
  - Research- Mining Maps, 1957-1962 (Box 10)
  - Research- News Releases, 1956-1962 (Box 10)
  - Research- Notes, 1956-1974 (Box 10)
  - Research- Photographs, 1960 (Box 10)
  - Research- Photographs- "Flow of Time", 1942-1963 (Box 10)
  - Research- Project Analysis, undated (Box 10)
  - Research- Dr. Paul Schaefer, 1969 (Box 10)
  - Research- Sybaris, 1963-1969 (Box 10)
  - Scientific Manpower Commission- Articles, 1962-1965 (Box 10)
  - Scientific Manpower Commission- Employment Records, 1957-1964 (Box 10)
  - Scientific Manpower Commission- Military Cases, 1963-1966 (Box 10)
  - Scientific Manpower Commission- Scientific & Engineering Mapower Organizational Directory, 1965 (Box 10)
  - Scientific Manpower Commission- Publications, 1962-1964 (Box 10)
  - Scientific Manpower Commission- SMC Comments, 1964 (Box 10)
  - Scientific Manpower Commission- Statements of Registered Manpower, 1963-1966 (Box 10)
  - Scientific Manpower Commission- Summaries, 1964-1965 (Box 10)
  - Smith College, 1949 (Box 10)
  - Speeches, 1959-1978 (Box 10)
  - US Joint Publication Research Service, 1968 (Box 10)
  - University of Pennsylvania, undated (Box 10)
  - Vanadium Corporation of America, 1947 (Box 10)
  - Writings- Arctic Perspective, undated (Box 11)
  - Writings- Basement Relief Beneath the Upper Cambrian of the Mid-Continent, 1968 (Box 11)
  - Writings- Book Reviews, 1968-1971 (Box 11)
  - Writings- Boston 1953 (Box 11)
  - Writings- Classification of Karst, 1973 (Box 11)
  - Writings- Educational Opportunities in the United States, undated (Box 11)
  - Writings- Enciclopedia del Petrolio e del Gas Naturale, undated (Box 11)
  - Writings- Geologic Factors Affecting the Search for Sybaris, undated (Box 11)
  - Writings- Geopolitics Revived, 1978 (Box 11)
  - Writings- Historical Geology Textbook- Advertising, 1930-1933 (Box 11)
  - Writings- Historical Geology Textbook- Editorial Comments, 1930-1931 (Box 11)
  - Writings- Historical Geology Textbook- Manuscript, 1930-1931 (Box 11)
  - Writings- Historical Geology Textbook- Outlines, 1930- (Box 11)
  - Writings- Hydrocarbon Province in the Gulf of Mexico?, 1969 (Box 11)
  - Writings- Mineral Raw Materials in the National Economy, 1962 (Box 11)
  - Writings- Political and Politic-Economic Outlook, undated (Box 11)
  - Writings- Study on the Petroleum Industry, undated (Box 11)
  - Writings- Tectonics of Eastern Caribbean Margin, undated (Box 11)